<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain considerations tending to promote peace and good will amongst Protestants very useful for the present times.</title>
            <author>Moderate conformist.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924519</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 732:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain considerations tending to promote peace and good will amongst Protestants very useful for the present times.</title>
                  <author>Moderate conformist.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edition of 1679 has on t.p.: "by a moderate conformist".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  England.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95459:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95459:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN CONSIDERATIONS Tending to promote PEACE AND GOOD WILL Amongſt <hi>PROTESTANTS:</hi> Very uſeful for the preſent Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:95459:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95459:2"/>
            <head>Conſiderations tending to promote Peace.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 Conſ.</hi> THat ſome of the moſt conſiderable ranks and orders of men, from the Reformation of Religion amongſt us, have manifeſted a deſire to have ſome Favour and Indulgence ſhew'd to Diſſenters in point of Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That Diſſenters or Non-conformiſts have often been miſrepreſented to the World.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The late Civil Wars in <hi>England</hi> were not begun for the extirpation of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, or to ſettle the Presbyterian Government here.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> That the Modern <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians as they are call'd, cannot be charged with divers of the Principles imputed to thoſe called Presbyterians in <hi>England</hi> in the dayes of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or to the Presbyterians in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> That there have been ſince the firſt Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> men of Parts, Piety, and Learning, and of good eſteem in the Church of God, who have boggled or ſcrupled at ſomething in Subſcription, or the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity injoyned or practiſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> That divers Diſſenters in former times have found fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with the Biſhops.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> That the Parliamentarians in the beginning of our Troubles declare to abhor and deteſt all deſigns of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing or Murthering His late Sacred Majeſty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> That the Non-conforming Presbyterians had both their hearts and hands in the Reſtauration of His preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to His Royal Throne.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:95459:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Many Biſhops, Clergy-men, and Scholars, though Non-conformiſts to the late times, then enjoyed Places of Profit notwithſtanding.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> That it is the declared Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in her 34th Article of Religion. That every Particular or National Church hath Authority to ordain, change, and aboliſh Ceremonies or Rites of the Church, ordained only by mans Authority, ſo that all things be done to Edification.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> That if the New Impoſitions and the Ceremonies ſhould happen to be legally taken away, many Thouſands who now ſtand aloof off would Joyn with our Church-Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> That the uſe of force or violent courſos for by Matters in Religion, ought by all lawful wayes and means to be ſhunned and avoided.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95459:3"/>
            <head>Certain Conſiderations tending to promote Peace and Good will amongſt Proteſtants, uſeful for the preſent Times.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nſtead of Preface, and to prepare the minds of men for ſuch Conſiderations as follow, I deſire the Reader to read certain excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſayings of the Reverend Dean of the Chappel, now Primate and Metropolitan of all <hi>England,</hi> in a Sermon of his Preached before the King <hi>June 28th.</hi> 1660. and after Printed, <hi>viz. I hat's the beſt the moſt Chriſtian Memorie, which as</hi> Caeſar, <hi>forgets nothing but Injuries.</hi>—Again, <hi>Let's all ſeriouſly and ſadly look back, conſider and bemoan one another for what we have mutually done and ſuffer'd from each other, let's all be ſorry for it, and all mend, perfectly forgiving what's paſt, and returning to as great a kindneſs as ever, and a greater then ever, that ſo by all mutual good Offices, we may make amends for former animoſities. Shall God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſo great, ſo glorious, after ſo high, ſo many Provocations, deſcend to be at peace with us, and ſhall we poor worms be at enmity among our ſelves for triſtes, and that to the hazard of all the comforts of this life, and hopes of a better?</hi> And further, <hi>ſhall we retain the memory of former unkindneſſes, and make a publick Act of Oblivion, which we expect, a Publick Lye? without either fear of God or ſhame of the world. This is not to have peace or enjoy it, but with great ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to throw it at him again; it is but to change one War into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the open into ſecret, hoſtility into treachery; and by pretending peace and kindneſs, to ſmooth the way to ſupplantation, and injury, the moſt baſe Serpentine, and unmanly thing in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Golden ſayings premiſed, I humbly offer theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations,</p>
            <div n="1" type="consideration">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95459:4"/>
               <head>1 Conſid. <hi>That ſome of the moſt conſiderable Ranks and Orders of men, ſince the Reformation of Religion amongſt us have manifeſted a deſire to have ſome favour, or Indulgence ſhewed to Diſſenters in point of Ceremonies,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. wrote a Letter to Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> in behalf of Mr. <hi>Hooper</hi> elected Biſhop of <hi>Gleuceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>RIght Reverend Father, and Right truſty and Well-beloved,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Whereas We by the advice of our Council, have called and choſen Our right Well-beloved, and well worthy Mr. <hi>John Hooper,</hi> to be Our Biſhop of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter;</hi> as well for his great Learning, due Judgment, and long ſtudy both in the Scriptures and other profound Learning; as alſo for his good diſcretion, ready utterance, and honeſt life, for that kind of Vocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from Conſecrating of whom We underſtand you do ſtay, becauſe he would have you omit certain Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies offenſive to his Conſcience, whereby ye think you ſhould fall in <hi>Praemunire</hi> of Lawes: We have thought good by advice aforeſaid, to diſpenſe and diſcharge you of all manner of dangers, penalties, and forfeitures you ſhould run into, and be in any manner of way, by omitting any of the ſame. And theſe Our Letters ſhall be your ſufficient Warrant and Diſcharge therefore.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Aug. 5th.</hi>
                           </date> 
                           <hi>Given under Our Signet at Our Caſtle of</hi> Windſor <date>
                              <hi>the fourth year of Our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>King <hi>James</hi> alſo wrote two Letters to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Non-conformiſts, one whereof you may read in D. <hi>Fuller's Hiſtory of the Church;</hi> Book the 9th. Page 203.</p>
               <p>After theſe, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed Memory, in His Anſwer to the Remonſtrance of the Houſe of Commons preſented to Him at <hi>Hampton Court, December</hi> the firſt, 1641.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95459:4"/>ſaith as follows, <hi>In differences amongſt Our ſelves, for matters indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in their own Nature, concerning Religion, we ſhall in tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to any number of our Loving Subjects, very willingly comply with the Advice of Our Parliament, that ſome Law may be made for the exemption of tender Conſciences from puniſhment, or proſecution for ſuch Ceremonies, and in ſuch Caſes, which, by the judgment of moſt men, are held to be matters indifferent, and of ſome to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely unlawful.</hi> And again in his Meſſage of the 20th. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. His Majeſty propoſeth to both Houſes of Parliament, the ſecurity of the true Religion now profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the ſetling of Ceremonies in ſuch a manner as may take away all juſt offence. In His Meſſage of the 14th. of <hi>February</hi> following, His Majeſty more fully expreſſeth himſelf, <hi>viz</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Becauſe His Majeſty obſerveth great and difficult troubles to ariſe in the hearts of his People concerning the Government and Liturgy of the Church, His Majeſty is willing to declare, that he will refer that whole Conſideration to the Wiſdom of His Parliament, which he deſires them to enter into ſpeedily, that the preſent Diſtempers about the ſame may be compoſed</hi>—Since, His moſt Gracious Majeſty that now is, and long and long may he continue our Soveraign Lord and King, hath often declared his willingneſs to Indulge tender Conſciences, witneſs his Declaration from <hi>Breda.</hi> His Declaration afterward <hi>October</hi> 8th. 1660. in which His Majeſty ſaith, <hi>Our preſent conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and work is to gratifie the private Conſciences of thoſe who are grieved with the uſe of ſome Ceremonies, by indulging to, and diſpenſing with the omitting of thoſe Ceremonies.</hi> Which Indulg nt Declaration ſo raviſhed the hearts of all Your Loving Subjects (ſaith a Member of the Houſe of Commons, in an Epiſtle to His Majeſty) that Your whole Houſe of Commons, their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, then Aſſembled in Parliament, immediately after the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, <hi>October</hi> the 9th. 1660. repaired in a Body to <hi>White-hall,</hi> and there by their Speakers Oration in the Banquetting-Houſe, expreſſed their extraordinary great joy, and preſented their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral thanks to Your Majeſty, for this Your Majeſties moſt Gracious Declaration and Diſpenſation, and with their Conſciences, in matters not being of the ſubſtance or eſſence of Religion; which gave abundant ſatisfaction to all peaceable ſober-minded men, and ſuch as are truly Religious, in which return of their thanks they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95459:5"/>were all unanimous, <hi>Nemine Contradicente.</hi> Then ordering a Bill in purſuance of Your Majeſties Declaration. <hi>Note;</hi> That this was that Houſe of Commons, which together with the Houſe of Lords, brought His Majeſty to His Throne. And hence we may infer that thoſe who are for indulgence to tender Conſciences, may be Good and Loyal Subjects to His Majeſty. I read, that in the dayes of King <hi>James,</hi> namely, in the Tenth year of His Reign, the Members of the Houſe of Commons thus Petition'd His Majeſty. <hi>Whereas divers painful and Learned Paſtors that have long time tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed in the work of the Miniſtrie, with good fruit and bleſſing of their Labours, have been removed from their Eccleſiaſtical Livings, being their Free-hold, and debarred from all means of maintenance, to the great grief of ſundry Your Majeſties well-affected Subjects; We therefore humbly beſeech Your Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed, that ſuch deprived and ſilenced Miniſters, living quietly and peaceably, may be reſtored,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Beames of former light,</hi> page 103. And in the Thirtieth year of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preſented to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal a Petition containing divers particulars, for the redreſs whereof they deſire, <hi>That no Oath or Subſcription might be tendered to any at their entrance into the Miniſtry, but ſuch as is expreſly preſcribed by the Statutes of this Realm, except the Oath againſt corrupt entring, That they may not be troubled for the Omiſſion of ſome Rites or portions preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer; That ſuch as had been ſuſpended or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived for no other offence, but only for not ſubſcribing, might be reſtored,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall ſet before you to conſider of the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſome of the Nobility. In the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, the great Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> wrote to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> for favour to Mr. <hi>Hooper</hi> then Lord Biſhop Elect of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi> The Letter we have recorded by Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi> to his Church Hiſtory, in theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>AFter my moſt hearty Commendations to your Grace, theſe may be to deſire the ſame that in ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things wherein this Bearer my Lord Elect of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> craveth to be born withall at your hands, you would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95459:5"/>vouchſafe to ſhew him your Graces favour, the rather at this my Inſtance, which thing partly I have taken in hand by the Kings Majeſties own motion. The matter is weighed by his Highneſs, none other, but that your Grace may facilely condeſcend thereunto. The Principal cauſe is, that you would not charge this ſaid Bearer with an Oath bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſom to his Conſcience. And ſo for lack of time, I commit your Grace to the tuition of Almighty God,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>July <hi>23. 1550.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your Graces moſt aſſured Loving Friend <hi>John Warwick.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>'Tis thought by the Hiſtorian that the Oath ſcrupled at, was the Oath of Canonical Obedience to the Arch-Biſhop, which conſequentially commanded ſuch Ceremonies, which <hi>Hooper</hi> was willing to decline.</p>
               <p>In the 26th year of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (if our Hiſtorian time it right) eight of the Privy Councel wrote a large Letter to the Biſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>London;</hi> towards the cloſe whereof there are theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>Now therefore we, for the diſcharge of our duties, being by our Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, under Her Majeſty bound to be careful that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Realm may be well Governed, to the Honour and Glory of God, and to the diſcharge of Her Majeſty, being the Principal Governor over all Her Subjects under Almighty God, do moſt earneſtly deſire your Lordſhips to take ſome charitable conſideration of theſe cauſes, that the People of this Realm may not be deprived of their Paſtors, being diligent, Learned and zealous, though in ſome points Ceremonial, they may ſeem doubtful only in Conſcience, and not of wilfulneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Lordſhips loving Friends
<list>
                              <item>Will. Burghley.</item>
                              <item>George Shrewsbury.</item>
                              <item>A. Warwick.</item>
                              <item>R. Leiceſter.</item>
                              <item>C. Howard.</item>
                              <item>J. Croft.</item>
                              <item>Cbr. Hatton.</item>
                              <item>Frae. Walſingham.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95459:6"/>
               <p>'Tis thought by Dr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> that Sir <hi>Francis Ruowles,</hi> Treaſurer of the Queens Houſhold, and Knight of the Garter, Father in Law to the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> was caſually abſent from the Council Board at this time, and that's the Reaſon he is miſs'd here amongſt the Privy Counſellors; for he was, ſaith he, a great Patron of the Non-conformiſts. Hereunto I ſhall add a paſſage at the Council Table concerning Mr. <hi>Paul Baines,</hi> a noted Non-conformiſt, he was called by Biſhop <hi>Harſnet</hi> to the Council Table, and accuſed for keeping of Conventicles and when he was accuſed hereof before the Privy Council, one of the Noble men ſaid, <hi>Speak, ſpeak for your ſelf,</hi> whereupon he made ſuch an Excellent Speech, that in the midſt thereof a Nobleman ſtood up and ſaid, <hi>He ſpeaks more like an Angel than a Man, and I dare not ſtay here to have a hand in any Sentence againſt him;</hi> upon which Speech they diſmiſſed him, and he never heard more from them.</p>
               <p>And now after Kings, the Commons in Parliament, and Lords of the Privy Council have appeared in this matter, give me leave to add the teſtimony of a Biſhop in the next place. It was the Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> and I think Biſhop <hi>Rudd.</hi> Hear him ſpeaking for Moderation and Condeſcention in his Speech to the reſt of the Biſhops in Convocation, <hi>May</hi> 23. 1604. and being dead, he yet ſpeaketh. <hi>I put great difference,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>between</hi> quod liceat <hi>and</hi> quod expediat, <hi>and likewiſe between them that are Schiſmatical, or open diſturbers of the State Eccleſiaſtical eſtabliſhed, and them that are ſcrupulous only upon ſome Ceremonies, and other Circumſtances, being otherwiſe Learned, Studious, Grave and Honeſt men, whoſe pains have been both painful in the Church, and profitable to their ſeveral Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; concerning theſe Preachers laſt mentioned, I ſuppoſe that if upon urging them to the uſe of Ceremonies and attire preſcribed, they ſhould ſtand out ſtiffly and chooſe rather to forego their Livings and the exerciſe of their Miniſtry. And though I do not juſtifie their doings therein, yet ſurely their Service would be miſſed at ſuch time us need ſhall require them, to give the right hand of fellowſhip one to another, and go arm in arm againſt the Common Adverſary, that ſo there might be</hi> vis Unita fortior, <hi>in which caſe, want of their joint labours with ours, there might ariſe cauſe of ſome ſuch doleful complaint as fell out upon an accident of another nature in the Book of</hi> Judges <hi>Chapter the</hi> 5.15, <hi>where it is ſaid that for the diviſions of</hi> Reuben, <hi>there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95459:6"/>were great thoughts of heart. Alſo remember that the</hi> Benjamites, <hi>though for their deſert, in maintaining a bad cauſe, were all deſtroyed ſaving Six hundred, and the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſwear in their fury that none of them would give his Daughter to Wife to the</hi> Benjamites, <hi>yet when their hot blood was over, they lamented, and ſaid, there is one Tribe cut off from</hi> Iſrael <hi>this day; and they uſed all their wits to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their policy to reſtore that Tribe again; In like ſort if thoſe our Brethren aforeſaid ſhould be deprived of their places, for the matters premiſed, I think we ſhould find cauſe to bend our wits to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extent of our Skill, to provide ſome Cure of Souls for them where they may exerciſe their Talents. Beſides this, foraſmuch as in the life-time of the late Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>theſe things were not ſo extreamly urged, but that many Learned Preachers injoyed their Liberty herein, conditionally that they did not by word or deed openly diſturb, or diſgrace the State eſtabliſhed, ☞ I would know a Reaſon why it ſhould now be ſo general and exceeding ſtrictly called upon, eſpecially ſeeing that theſe men are now the men neceſſary by ſo much we ſee the greater increaſe of Papiſts to be of late then were before. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I wiſh I wiſh, that if by Petition made to the Kings Majeſty there cannot be obtained a juite removall of the Premiſes, which ſeem ſo grievous to divers; nor yet a toleration for them which be of the more ſtay'd and temperate carriage; yet at leaſt there might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a mitigation of the penalty, if they cannot be drawn by other Reaſons to a conformity with us.</hi> See <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>F. L.</hi> p. 205. And now to this Biſhops excellent Speech, let me ſubjoyn what I find in Print, by a Son of the Church, I may ſay by a great Champion and Pillar of the Proteſtant Church, in his Preface to the Reader before his <hi>Irenicum, What Charter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath Chriſt given the Church to bind men up to more then himſelf hath done? or to exclude thoſe from Society, who may be admitted into Heaven? It is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the things commanded and required be lawful or no; it is not how Chriſtians are bound to ſubmit to a reſtraint of their Chriſtian Liberty which I now inquire after</hi> (of theſe things in the Treatiſe it ſelf) <hi>but whether they do conſult for the Churches peace, and unity, who ſuſpend it upon ſuch things; how far either the example of our Saviour or his Apoſtles do warrant ſuch rigorous Impoſitions. We never read of the Apoſtles making Laws, but of things ſuppoſed neceſſary—It was not enough with them, that the things would be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95459:7"/>neceſſary when they had required them, but they looked on an Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent neceſſity, either abſolute or for the preſint State, which was the only ground of impoſing thoſe commands upon the Gentile Chriſtians —would there ever be the leſs unity in a Church, if a diverſity was allowed as to practiſes ſuppoſed Indifferent; yea, there would be ſo much the more, as there was a mutual forbearance and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to ſuch things.</hi> And a little after ſpeaking of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church; he adds, <hi>It was never thought worth the while to make any ſtanding Law for Rites and Cuſtoms, that had no other Original but Tradition. Much leſs to ſuſpend men her Communion for not obſerving them.—The firſt who broke this Order in the Church, were the</hi> Arrians, Donatiſts, <hi>and</hi> Circumcellians, <hi>whil'ſt the true Church was ſtill known by its priſtine Moderation and ſweetneſs of deportment towards all its Members. The ſame we hope may remain, and the moſt infallible evidence of the Conformity of our Church of</hi> England <hi>to the Primitive, not ſo much in uſing the ſame Rites as were in uſe then, as in not impoſing them, but leaving men to be won, by the obſerving the true decency and order of Churches, whereby thoſe who act upon a Principle of Chriſtian Ingenuity, may be ſooner drawn to a compliance in all lawful things, than by force and rigorous Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which made men ſuſpect the weight of the thing it ſelf when ſuch force is uſed to make it enter. In the mean time, what cauſe have we to rejoyce that Almighty God hath been pleaſed to reſtore us a Prince of that Excellent Prudence and Moderation, who hath ſo lately given aſſurance to the world of his great Indulgence towards all, that have any pretence from Conſcience to differ from their brethren.</hi> From the Premiſes it appears abundantly that Diſſenters and Scruplers in by-matters have had ſome Friends as well as many Enemies, and the Reaſon they have had no more Friends, has certainly been a Miſ-repreſentation of them to the world as Seditious and Turbulent perſons, Enemies to <hi>Caeſar</hi> and all good Government and Order in Church and State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="consideration">
               <p>And this uſhers in our ſecond Conſideration; namely, <hi>That Diſſenters or Non-conformiſts have been frequently falſly repreſented to the world.</hi> Of old the <hi>Jews</hi> not worſhipping the ſame Gods that the <hi>Ægyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> and other Nations did, were accuſed to worſhip an Aſſes head, and once a year to Sacrifice a <hi>Graecian</hi> according to their Rites and Ceremonies, and to taſte and cat of his entrails, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95459:7"/>in the Sacrificing of the <hi>Grecian,</hi> to Swear to be Enemies to the <hi>Greeks.</hi> v. loſephus <hi>in his Second Book againſt</hi> Apion. Our bleſſed Saviour himſelf was accuſed to be an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Holy Apoſtles were charged to turn the world upſide down. The Primitive Chriſtians were Judged to be Atheiſts becauſe they would not worſhip the Gods of the Heathens, on them was laid the blame of all the Plagues, and Droughts, and Famines, and Wars, and what ever elſe was hurtful to Mankind, as you may read in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> his firſt Book <hi>adverſus Gentes.</hi> Of later times the Papiſts have charged the Proteſtants as the Authors of Rebellion and Sedition.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> had a Book which was given a Neighbor of his (when taken and carried to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> to make him a good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick) the Title was <hi>Monarcho Machia,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Babel;</hi> wherein the Author labours to maintain that the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Presbyterian Diſcipline, were in all parts introduced and upheld by Sedition and Rebellion: To make this good, he chargeth <hi>Calvin</hi> with ſuch Seditious Doctrine, as the Proteſtant Leaders built their Rebellion upon. To prove that <hi>Calvin</hi> by his Doctrine diſchargeth men of Oaths made to their Soveraigns, he alledgeth his Fourth Book, Chap. 13. Paragraph the 21, ſaying, <hi>a man illuminate with the truth, Simul vinculis omnibus obediendi legibus &amp; Eccleſiae ſolutus eſt. He that once hath perfect knowledge of the Goſpel, is abſolved from Oaths, and all ſuch Snares.</hi> Now turn to the place in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Inſtitutions, and you ſhall ſoon deſcry palpable Knavery. For <hi>Calvin</hi> in all that whole Chapter hath not one word of ſuch Oaths of Allegiance as Subjects take to their Soveraigns. He treateth only of Monaſtical or Monkiſh Vows, of theſe, not of thoſe; his words are only theſe, <hi>Nunc poſtquam veritatis notitia ſunt illuminati, ſimul Chriſti gratia liberos eſſe dico.</hi> That is, <hi>Now they,</hi> to wit, <hi>who formerly had made ſuch unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Vows, and out of Error and Ignorance held themſelves obliged therewith, after they are inlightned with notice of the truth, are, I ſay, free by the grace of God.</hi> To this, as Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> obſerves, the ſame Author adds another as groſs and palpable as the former. Theſe ſeditious and popular Conſiſtories, ſaith he, the Presbyteries, he means, are condemned by their half-brethren the <hi>Zuinglians.</hi> Hear, ſaith he, the voyce of <hi>Gualterus</hi> a Miniſter of <hi>Zurich,</hi> how
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95459:8"/>bitter a Sentence he pronounceth againſt them in his Commentary on 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> Cap. 5th. <hi>Galli habent ſua Seniorum Conſiſtoria penes quos eſt omnis poteſtas &amp; Jurisdictio Eccleſiaſtica; &amp; in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnium Bellorum contra Regem, &amp; conſilia acta, &amp; ſubſidia collecta ſunt.</hi> That is, <hi>The</hi> French-<hi>Miniſters have their Conſiſtories of Elders, in whom reſteth the Supremacy of Jurisdiction in all cauſes Eccleſiaſtical; and by theſe all Counſels and Reſolutions are taken, and all Impoſitions appointed to maintain the Wars againſt the King.</hi> Thus the aforeſaid nameleſs Author, but ſaith Mr. <hi>Gattaker,</hi> let any man ſedulouſly peruſe, as my ſelf have done, the whole Commentary of <hi>Gualter</hi> upon that Chapter conſiſting of, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in four Sermons, and he ſhall find not one title there, either of the <hi>French</hi> King, or of the <hi>French</hi> Conſiſtory, or of ought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted or enacted, or acted in the one againſt the other. He ſpeaks indeed in the ſecond Sermon on that Chapter, <hi>of the Popes Excommunications, wherewith,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they cruelly vexed Kings and Emperors, and were Authors of Civil Wars and Seditions; deemeth the Presbyteriall Government, not ſo needfvl under a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; but leaveth every Church free, to that courſe of Diſcipline that they ſhall find to be for themſelves moſt commodious, without cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of others, who therein differ from them;</hi> And this is all he hath there of this Argument. But this obſcure Fellow, for the further confirmation of theſe his fictions and falſhoods, ſends us to <hi>Muſculus</hi> his Common Places, Chap. 10. <hi>Title de Officiis Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Muſculus</hi> in his Common Places. <hi>Loc.</hi> 22. Title the 2d. <hi>De Officiis Miniſtrorum,</hi> hath much indeed of the pride formality, either no Preaching, or unprofitable Diſcourſe of the Popiſh Prelates and Prieſts. Of the Presbyterie not a word good or bad. See Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> his Vindication of the Annotations on <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Tenth, <hi>2d. v. pag.</hi> 15, 16. I cannot tell whether ever Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> did meet with this Popiſh Author, or no; and whether he did Plough with his Heifer in the Hiſtory of the Presbyterians; yet ſurely he may very well be yoaked with him, for he chargeth the Churches reformed and model'd after the <hi>Calvinian</hi> Mode of Government in the Low Countreys, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> with Rebellion and Treaſon. But as good hap is, a moſt Learned Biſhop of our own Church in his Treatiſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Subjection, pag. 521. excuſeth the <hi>Germans, Flemings,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95459:8"/>
                  <hi>Scots</hi> from Rebellion. <hi>Why ſhould the Germans,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſubmitting themſelves to the Emperor at his Election but on condition, not injoy the ſame liberties and ſecurities of their publick State, which their Fathers did before them? Why ſhould they be accounted Rebels for preſerving their Politie, more than the</hi> Italians, <hi>who cut themſelves utterly from the Empire, by no conſent or allowance, but only force and diſturbance. The ſame we ſay for the</hi> Flemings <hi>what Reaſon the King of</hi> Spain <hi>ſhould alter their State, and avert their ancient Lawes, his Style declaring him not to be King, but Earl of</hi> Flanders, <hi>and being admitted for a Protector, if he will needs become an Oppreſſor, why ſhould they not defend the Freedome of their Countrey? The</hi> Scots, <hi>what have they done, beſides placing the right Heir, and he an own Son, when the Mother fled and forſook the Realm? Be theſe thoſe Furious Attempts and Rebellions you talk of?</hi> So Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> againſt his Romiſh Adverſary. And now that Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> hath ſpoken. Let the Prieſt or Presbyter Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> hold his tongue. And let one of his own Order be heard ſpeak in the like caſe. 'Tis Doctor <hi>Peter Du Moulin,</hi> Canon of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and one of His Majeſties Chaplains. He vindicates the City of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and the Introduction of Reformation into that State from the Crime of Rebellion. <q>It is utterly falſe, ſaith he in his Anſwer to <hi>Philanax Anglicus,</hi> pag. 28. that <hi>Calvin</hi> was one of the Planters of the Reformed Religion at <hi>Geneva;</hi> falſe alſo, that He, or the Reformers of <hi>Geneva</hi> turned their Biſhop out of dores; and falſe alſo that the Biſhop went away upon the quarrel of Religion. <hi>Farell, Fromont,</hi> and <hi>Viret,</hi> were they that wrought under God the Converſion of the City, by their Sermons, and by a publick Conference with the Fryers and Clergy of <hi>Geneva,</hi> there being then no Biſhop in that Town, he was fled eight Moneths before, ſeeing his Conſpiracy diſcovered to oppreſs the Liberties of the City, by the help of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> for which his Secretary was Hang'd, after the Biſhop was gone; the ſaid Biſhop being hated before for the Rape of a Virgin, and many Adulteries with Citizens Wives: And 'tis moſt to be noted, that they who after his flight reformed the civil Government, were ſtrong Papiſts, and mainly oppoſed the Reformation of Religion.</q> How the aforeſaid Dr. <hi>Moulin</hi> vindicates the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants from Treaſon and Rebellion may be ſeen at large in the Treatiſe before cited,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95459:9"/>
                  <hi>p.</hi> 30 31, 32, &amp;c. I ſhall here inſert as to the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants Loyalty the Teſtimony of King <hi>James,</hi> who was a great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, Jealous of the Royal Authority, cited by the aforeſaid Author. <hi>Inever yet knew,</hi> ſaith King <hi>James, That the</hi> French <hi>Proteſtants took Arms againſt their King; In the firſt troubles they ſtood only upon their defence, before they took Arms, they were burnt and maſſacred every where; and the quarrel did not begin for Religion, but becauſe when King</hi> Francis <hi>the Second was under Age, they had been the Refuge of the Princes of the blood expel'd from Court, even of the Grandfather of this King now Reigning, and of that of the Prince of</hi> Conde, <hi>who knew not where to take Sanctuary: for which the preſent King hath reaſon to wiſh them well: It ſhall not be found that they made any other War. Nay, is it not true that King</hi> Henry <hi>the Third ſent Armies againſt them to deſtroy them, and yet they came to his help as ſoon as they ſaw him in danger. Is it not true that they ſaved his life at</hi> Tours, <hi>and delivered him from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream peril? Is it not true that they never forſook him nor his Succeſſors in the midſt of the revolt and Rebellion, of moſt part of the Kingdom raiſed by the Pope, and the greateſt part of the Clergy? Is it not true that they have aſſiſted him in all his Battels, and helped much to raiſe the Crown again, which was ready to fall? Is it not true that they which perſecuted the late King</hi> Henry <hi>the Fourth, injoy this day the Fruits of the Services done by the Proteſtants? Such a Judgment, ſaith Dr.</hi> Du Moulin <hi>is of good weight, coming from a wiſe King, who was truly informed of the buſineſs of his Neighbours.</hi> And if ſo, then Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> ſurely was miſ-informed himſelf, and hath miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented the Caſe of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants to the world in his late Hiſtory of the Presbyterians, as he hath alſo done of the <hi>Netherland</hi> and <hi>Scots.</hi> For the Reformed Religion, ſaith Dr. <hi>P. Du Moulin</hi> was ſpread in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> over the Seventeen Provinces many years before there was any thought of making an Union againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and neither was that Union made upon the ſcore of Religion; but of State for maintaining their Franchiſes, againſt the oppreſſion of <hi>Spain:</hi> As it was ſufficiently juſtified by their chuſing <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of <hi>Alenſon</hi> a Roman Catholick for their Prince. So here, for a farther clearing of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> from Rebellion. Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> tells us, that after Reaſons had been urged before Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to prove them Rebels; Her
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95459:9"/>Majeſty reſolved, that it was both Chriſtian Piety to relieve the afflicted <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> embracers of the ſame Religion She pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and Wiſdom to provide for the ſafety of Her People. And again he tells us, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1587. the States in Parliament, (where were the Biſhops alſo) congratulated Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as for good Laws, ſo for the <hi>French</hi> King and the <hi>Netherlands</hi> relieved. 'Tis worth the obſervation that Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> looked on the Presbyterians in <hi>Holland,</hi> as of the ſame Religion with themſelves, notwithſtanding the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Church-Government and Ceremonies. Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> obſerves out of <hi>John Bodin</hi> an Ingenuous and Judicious Writer, and a Papiſt himſelf, an Author of good note amongſt Papiſts and Proteſtants both, a notable commendation of <hi>Geneva.</hi> See <hi>Method. Hiſtor. cap.</hi> 6. <hi>page</hi> 245 <hi>That of the</hi> Genevians, ſaith <hi>Bodin, is landable if ought in any Nation, and that which makes a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to flouriſh, if not in Riches and Majeſtical Empire, yet ſure in Piety and Virtue, to wit the Pontificial Cenſure,</hi> (ſo he calls the Eccleſiaſtical or Presbyterial Diſcipline)—<hi>In that City therefore no Harlotry, no Drunkenneſs, no Dancings, no Beggars, no idle perſons, are found.</hi> The aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> to clear thoſe of the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> way from Sedition, tells us a Story of Biſhop <hi>Elmor,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, <hi>viz.</hi> that when one Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs</hi> had inveighed bitterly againſt the Puritans, as a crew of ſeditious and turbulent perſons, and had affirmed the Puritans to be worſe than the Papiſts; <hi>No,</hi> quoth the Biſhop, <hi>he ſaid not therein aright, for the Puritans if they had me amongſt them would cut my Rochet only, but the Papiſts would cut my Throat.</hi> The ſame Author Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi> tells us, that his Succeſſor Biſhop <hi>Vaughan,</hi> when another in the ſame place, was no leſs eager in the ſame Argument, the Biſhop ſaid to a Gentleman of his inward Acquaintance who Dined that day with him (as the Gentleman himſelf told Mr. <hi>Gattaker</hi>) <hi>I wiſh I could have had the Preachers Tongue to day for ſome ſpace of time in my Pocket, The way is not to convert or convince that party by Invectives and untruths. It is true they affect not the preſent form of Government, they are for another; but they ſeek it by Petition, not by Inſurrection or Sedition.</hi> And further to balance Dr. <hi>P. H</hi>'s teſtimony againſt the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and Presbyterians, and to undeceive well-minded perſons
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95459:10"/>who read his Hiſtory of Presbyterians, and believe him on that ſubject as much as they do his Comment on the Creed it ſelf; It will not be amiſs to cite here ſome paſſages out of Mr. <hi>Bedel,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Biſhop <hi>Bedel,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> who objected againſt the Reformed Religion, what Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> doth againſt the <hi>Calvinian</hi> Reformers, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were the cauſe of Sedition and Rebellion. <q>You have wronged, ſaith Mr. <hi>Bedel,</hi> thoſe you have named, and either lightly believed or unjuſtly ſurmiſed your ſelf touching <hi>Luther, Calvin, Knox,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders:</hi> when you make them the raiſers of Rebellion, and ſhedders of blood, whoſe blood hath been ſhed like water in all parts of thoſe Countreys, againſt all Laws of God and Man, againſt the Edicts, and publick Faith, till neceſſity enforced them to ſtand for their lives. <hi>Pag.</hi> 136. As for the War in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſaith the ſame Author, it began not till after <hi>Luthers</hi> death; neither was it a Rebellion of the Proteſtants; the truth is, they ſtood for their Lives. The Emperor with the help of the Popes both Money and Arms, intended to root them out, and although at the firſt the Emperor did not avow his raiſing Arms againſt them to be for Religion; yet the Pope in his <hi>Jubilee</hi> publiſhed upon this occaſion, did not let to declare to the world, that himſelf and <hi>Caeſar</hi> had concluded a League, to reduce the Hereticks by force of Arms to the obedience of the Church, and therefore all ſhould pray for the good ſucceſs of the War.</q> So the ſame Author pag. 124. <q>As for <hi>Calvin,</hi> he ſaith, he did not by his unquietneſs and Ambition revolve the State of <hi>Geneva,</hi> unjuſtly expelling, and depriving the Biſhop of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and other Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Lords of their due obedience, and ancient inheritance, for he came to <hi>Geneva</hi> 1536. but <hi>Bodin</hi> in his Second Book <hi>de Repub. Chap.</hi> 6. affirmed, and that in the ſame year <hi>Geneva</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed a State Ariſtocratical, which was he ſaith 1528. <hi>Geneva</hi> changed from a Monarchy Pontifical, into an eſtate Popular, governed Ariſtocratically; although that long before the Town pretended to be free againſt the Earl and againſt the Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Further, whereas Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> layes to the <hi>Hugonots</hi> and <hi>Ghenſes</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the raiſing of Civil Wars, ſhedding of Blood, occaſioning Rebellions, Rapines, Deſolations, principally for their new Religion, Mr. <hi>Bedel,</hi> afterwards Biſhop <hi>Bedel,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95459:10"/>
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 132. <q>Theſe poor people having endured ſuch barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Cruelties, Maſſacres, and Martyrdoms, as ſcarce the like can be ſhewed in all Stories, are now accuſed by you as the Authors of all they ſuffered. No, no, Mr. <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> they be the Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion that are written in blood; It is the bloody Inquiſition, and the perfidious violating of the Edicts of Pacification, that have ſet <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> in combuſtion. An evident Argument may be for <hi>Flanders,</hi> that thoſe <hi>Ghenſes</hi> which you mention were no <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> as you are mis-informed, the chief of them were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, as namely, Count <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> and <hi>Horn,</hi> who both loſt their Heads, for ſtanding, and yet only by Petition, againſt the new Impoſitions, and the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which was ſought to be brought in upon thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. And after <hi>pag.</hi> 134. you would know, <hi>quo Juri,</hi> the Proteſtants Wars in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> are juſtified. Firſt, <hi>ſaith Mr.</hi> Bedel, the Law of Nature, which not only alloweth, but inforceth every living thing to defend it ſelf from violence. Secondly, that of Nations, which permitteth thoſe that are in the Protection of others, to whom they owe no more than an Honourable acknowledgment, in caſe they go about to make themſelves abſolute Soveraigns, and uſurp their Liberty to ſtand for the ſame. And if a lawful Prince, which (ſaith he) is not yet Lord of his Subjects lives and goods) ſhall attempt to deſpoil them of the ſame, under colour of reducing them to his own Religion, after all humble Remonſtrances, they may ſtand upon their own guard, and being aſſailed, may repell force with force, as did the <hi>Machabees</hi> under <hi>Antiochus.</hi> In which caſe notwithſtanding the perſon of the Prince himſelf ought always to be ſacred and inviolable, as was <hi>Sauls</hi> to <hi>David.</hi> And laſtly, if the enraged Miniſter of a lawful Prince will abuſe his Authority againſt the Fundamental Laws of the Countrey, it is no Rebellion to defend themſelves againſt reſerving ſtill their obedience to their Soveraign inviolate. Theſe are the rules of which the Proteſtants that have born Arms in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> and the Papiſts alſo both there and elſewhere as in <hi>Naples,</hi> that have ſtood for the defence of their Liberties, have ſerved themſelves, how truly, I eſteem it hard for you and me to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, unleſs we were more throughly acquainted with the Laws
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95459:11"/>and Cuſtoms of thoſe Countreys, then I for my part am. Once for the Low Countreys, the world knows that the Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> were not Kings or abſolute Lords of them, which are holden partly of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and partly of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and of <hi>Holland</hi> in particular, they were but Earls. And whether that title carries with it ſuch a Soveraignty, as to be able to give new Laws without their conſents, to impoſe Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, to bring in Garriſons of Strangers, to build Forts aſſubject their Honours and Lives to the dangerous trial of a new Court, proceeding without form or figure of Juſtice, any reaſonable man may well doubt; themſelves do utterly deny it.</q> So far Mr. <hi>Bedel,</hi> afterwards Biſhop <hi>Bedel,</hi> Yea, Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi> ſpeaking of the Seventeen Provinces in his Hiſtory of the Presbyterians, <hi>pag</hi> 96. <q>Grants that all of them were Priviledged ſo far, as to ſecure them all without a manifeſt violation of their Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from the fear of Bondage. But none ſo amply priviledged, ſaith he, as the Province of <hi>Brabant,</hi> to which it had been granted by ſome well-meaning, but weak Prince amongſt them, that if their Prince or Duke (by which name they call'd him) ſhould by ſtrong hand attempt the violation of their ancient Priviledges, the Peers and People might proceed to a new Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and put themſelves under the Clientele or Patronage of ſome juſter Governor.</q> D. <hi>P. H. Hiſt. of the Presb.</hi> p. 96.</p>
               <p>As for the Stirs, Broils, Seditions and Murthers in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> imputes to <hi>Knox,</hi> and the <hi>Geneva</hi> Goſpellers, as he calls them, Mr. <hi>Bedel</hi> before cited, <hi>p.</hi> 128, 129. Anſwers, <q>They might be occaſioned perhaps by the Reformers there, as the broils which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſaith he, came to ſet in the world by the Goſpel. Poſſible alſo, that good men out of inconſiderate Zeal ſhould do ſomething raſhly. And like enough the multitude which followed them, as being fore-prepared with a juſt hatred of the Tyrannie of their Prelates, and provoked by the oppoſition of the adverſe Faction, and emboldened by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, ran a great deal farther, then either wiſemen could foreſee or tell how to reſtrain them; of all which diſtempers there is no reaſon to lay the blame upon the ſeekers of Reformation, more than upon the Phyſicians of ſuch Accidents, as happen to the corrupted bodies which they have in Cure—as for the purſuing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95459:11"/>our King even before his birth, that which His Majeſty ſpeaks of ſome Puritans, is over boldly by you referr'd to Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> and the Miniſters that were Authors of Reformation in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </q> And Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> to his Antagoniſt ſaith thus, <hi>The</hi> Scots <hi>what have they done?</hi> Beſides, <hi>placing the right Heir on the Throne, and he an own Son, when the Mother fled and forſook the Realm. Be theſe thoſe furious Attempts and Rebellions you talk of?</hi> Dr. <hi>Rivet</hi> as he is quoted by Dr. <hi>Peter Du Moulin</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Philanax An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicus, imputes not the troubles in</hi> Scotland, <hi>in the dayes of the Queen Regent, and her Daughter</hi> Mary <hi>to the Reformed Religion, but to the hot and audacious brains, or to the bold and ſtirring nature of the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Nation,</hi> yea, it ſhall be found, as <hi>de Rivet</hi> obſerveth; and we find it now <hi>ſaith Dr.</hi> Du Moulin, <hi>that the light of Evangelical truth did very much mitigate the fierceneſs of that Nation, and that thoſe diſorders as turbulent as they were, are not comparable to thoſe that were in former times in</hi> Scotland. And laſtly, as to this particular, hear what Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> ſaith, namely, that <hi>the Confederacy of the Nobility of</hi> Scotland <hi>was not to be branded with the note of Rebellion which was made to no other purpoſe than to preſerve the Kingdom, as in Duty they ought, to the Queen and her lawful Succeſſors, which they could not without injury to themſelves and theirs, ſuffer to be undermined by the practiſes of the</hi> Guiſes, <hi>or ſo to be transferred to the</hi> French.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="consideration">
               <head>3. Conſid. <hi>The late Civil Wars in</hi> England <hi>were not begun for the Extirpation of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, or the ſettlement of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Houſe of Commons in the year 1640. had but few, I have heard not five Presbyterians in it. Beſides Mr. <hi>Richard Watſon</hi> cited by the Author of the <hi>Friendly Debate,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to the 3d. Part.</note> and no Friend I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le aſſure you to Presbyterie, he ſaith in his Hiſtory, That when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners came into <hi>Scotland,</hi> after the War had been near a year in <hi>England;</hi> and brought a Letter to the Aſſembly there, from the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> they received no other Anſwer but this, <hi>Gentlemen, we are ſorry for your Caſe, but whereas your Letter ſaith you fight for the defence of the Proteſtant Religion, you muſt needs think us blind that we ſee not your fighting to be for Civil diſputes of the Law, which we are not acquainted withall; Go home and reconcile with the King, he is a Gracious Prince, and will receive you to his favour,</hi> &amp;c. It ſeems by this paſſage that the War
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95459:12"/>was not begun on the Accompt of Church Government or Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Again, Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> in his Remonſtrance tells the world <hi>the only quarrel was, and is, the Militia, for which ſo much blood hath been ſpent and treaſure.</hi> 'Tis obſervable that the two Houſes juſt before the breaking out of the War, <hi>viz. April 9th.</hi> 1642. publiſhed a Declaration, wherein are theſe words. <hi>The Lords and Commons do declare that they intend a due and Neceſſary Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the Government and Liturgy of the Church, and to take away nothing in the one or the other, but what ſhall be civil or juſtly offenſive, or at leaſt unneceſſary and burdenſom</hi>—This Declaration of the Lords and Commons was Printed and Ordered to be publiſhed by the Sheriffs in ſeveral Counties in all the Market Towns within the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover in the 8th. of the 19 Propoſitions ſent by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to His Majeſty, <hi>June</hi> 2. 1642. <hi>The Lords and Commons deſire, that His Majeſty would be pleaſed that ſuch a Reformation be made of the Church Government, and Liturgy as both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall adviſe, wherein they intend to have Conſultation with Divines.</hi> And <hi>His Majeſty</hi> in his Anſwer to the 19 Propoſitions <hi>takes ſpeciall notice, that they ſeem in their 8th. Propoſition to deſire but a Reformation, and not a deſtruction of the preſent Diſcipline and Liturgy.</hi> Hitherto then, <hi>viz. June</hi> 2. 1642. the two Houſes of Parliament were for a Reformation only, and not for the abolition of Epiſcopacy and Liturgy. 'Tis acknowledged that afterwards there was a League and Covenant for the extirpation of Prelacy. But yet they who took the Covenant were bound only to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it in their places and Callings, and ſo far as lawfully they might, and men were told in thoſe dayes from the Preſs and Pulpit, that they might take the Covenant in a ſenſe not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of, or deſtructive to a Primitive Epiſcopacy. After this when the four Bills were ſent to His Majeſty to the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> upon ſigning whereof, the Parliament offer'd to treat for all the reſt in difference. The Bill for the Abolition of Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops was none of the four. In the year 1648. the Houſe of Commons voted His Majeſties Conceſſions a Ground of Peace notwithſtanding His Majeſty had not conſented to the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Epiſcopacy, only it was, 'tis ſaid, agreed betwixt the King and the Commiſſioners, that Biſhops ſhould be laid aſide
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95459:12"/>for three years till the King and the Parliament ſhould agree upon ſome ſetled Order for the Church, and upon a free debate had with the Aſſembly of Divines then ſitting, and twenty more of His Majeſties nomination, they might 'tis ſaid, have admitted of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, if they found that Government moſt agreeable to the Word of God, and beſt Reformed Churches. Laſtly, as to this Conſideration His Majeſty that now is, and long, and long may he continue to Reign over us, hath declared, that the Presbyterian Miniſters he had diſcourſed withall, could ſubmit to a Primitive Epiſcopacy and a Reformed Liturgy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="consideration">
               <head>4. Conſid. <hi>That the Modern</hi> Engliſh <hi>Presbytcrians as they are call'd, cannot be charged with divers of the Principles imputed to thoſe called Presbyterians in</hi> England, <hi>in the days of Q</hi> Elizabeth. <hi>And that the Presbytery, where it was voted by the Houſes of Parliament to be ſetled, was far different from the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Presbytery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Doctor <hi>P. Heylin</hi> tells us that Mr. <hi>T. C.</hi> and others, formerly renounced the Orders they had from the hands of the Biſhops, and look a new Vocation from the Presbyters beyond Seas; that the Presbyterians in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> crected their Diſcipline in <hi>England,</hi> without Authority from the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; that they held the calling of Biſhops unlawful, that 'tis not lawful to be ordained by them; that 'tis not lawful to appear in a Biſhops Court, but with a Proteſtation of their unlawfulneſs. —Theſe are not the Principles and Practices of the preſent Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Non-conformiſts amongſt us, they do not renounce their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Orders. Some of them have been ordained by Biſhops ſince 1660. Yea, are willing to ſubmit to the Government of the Church by Biſhops, and to uſe the Liturgy. <hi>Only they bum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire that the new Impoſitions by the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> 1662. <hi>may be taken away, and ſome of them that they may be diſpenſed withall for the three Ceremonies which are of their own Nature In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different even in the Judgment of the Impoſers;</hi> And which we are told were offer'd to have been abated in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> if that would have given ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>And as for the late <hi>Presbiterian Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> if you will have it called ſo, they differed much from the Aſſemblies of the Church of <hi>Scotland. They at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>attribute power</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>P. Heylin to the civil Magiſtrate, not only of calling Synods
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95459:13"/>and Church-Aſſemblies, but alſo of being preſent at them, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide that whatſoever is therein concluded be done agreeably to the mind and will of God. As to the matter of Church Government, the divine right of their Presbyteries, the ſetting up of Chriſt upon his Throne, the Parity or Imparity of Miniſters in the Church of Chriſt not a word delivered.</hi> And a little after he adds: <hi>It is to be obſerved that in the ſetling of the Presbyterian Government in</hi> England, <hi>as the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries were to be ſubordinate to the Claſſical Provincial and National Aſſemblies of the Church, ſo were they all, to be ſubordinate to the power of the Parliament, as appears plainly by the Ordinance of the</hi> 14th <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>which makes it quite another thing from the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Presbiteries, and other Aſſemblies of that Kirk, which hold themſelves to be Supream and unaccountable in their actings, without reſpect to the King, the Parliament and the Courts of Juſtice:</hi> So the Hiſtorian pag. 475. of his Hiſtory of the Presbyterians. And as for thoſe of the Congregational way here, they do not pretend to exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from all judgement or cenſure, from the civil Magiſtrate, or neighbouring Churches, if we may believe the Apologiſts in their Apologitical narration, p. 21. where they tell us that at a time when they had leaſt dependency on this Kingdom, or ſo much as hopes ever to abide therein in peace, it was openly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſſed, That it was the moſt to be abhorred Maxim, that any Religion hath ever made profeſſion of, and therefore of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt contradictory, and diſhonourable to that of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; that a ſingular and particular ſociety of men, profeſſing the name of Chriſt, and pretending to be endued with a power from Chriſt, to Judge them who are of the ſame body and ſociety within themſelves, ſhould further arrogate unto themſelves an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from giving an account, or being cenſurable by any other, either Chriſtian Magiſtrate above them, or neighbour Churches about them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="consideration">
               <head>5. Conſid. <hi>That there have been ſince the firſt Reformation, men of parts, Piety, Learning, and of good eſteem in the Church of God, who have yet boggled or ſcrupled at ſomething in ſubſcription, or the conformity injoined or practiſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th his Reign, there were Biſhop <hi>Hooper, Rogers, Philpot,</hi> and others, who diſguſted the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95459:13"/>
               <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, <hi>Coverdale,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> tells us, waved the acceptation of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Oxon,</hi> or any other vacant, out of a diſaffection to the Habit of that Order. He ſayes further, That <hi>Alexander Nowel</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> ſpoke irreverently of the Sign of the Croſs. Moreover he makes Mr. <hi>John Fox</hi> the the Martyrologiſt; <hi>Sampſon</hi> Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxfod; Hardiman</hi> a Prebendary of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> both the Profeſſors of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity in the Univerſities; and <hi>Whittington</hi> Dean of <hi>Durham,</hi> all Non-Conformiſts, and relates that one <hi>Whitehead</hi> who had been Chaplain to <hi>Ann Bullen</hi> the Queens Mother, was offered the Amh-Biſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> but refuſed it, becauſe he was more inclined to the Presbyterians than the Epiſcopal form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Beſides, we are told that <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> never could be got to wear the Surplice all the time that he was in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Divinity Reader in that Univerſity. Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> alſo tells us that Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> dreaded bowing at the name of Jeſus; and as we are informed, oppoſed the introduction of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ceremonies into the Church of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Not long before the Wars, Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cleaver,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and others of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent worth, were ſilenced for Non-Conformity, on which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, a Conformiſt of good note, in the life of Dr. <hi>Harris,</hi> thus expreſſes himſelf, <hi>Now was there a fearful Eclipſe upon the Church, a Conſtellation of Miniſters even at once darkned; amongſt the reſt, thoſe three ſhining Stars, Mr.</hi> Dod, <hi>Mr.</hi> Cleaver, <hi>Mr.</hi> Lancaſter. <hi>Mr.</hi> Dod <hi>was a very eloquent man, he ſaith, in Engliſh and Latine, ſo facetious and pithy, that Mr.</hi> Harris <hi>would often ſay, that if his</hi> Apothegms <hi>were collected, they would exceed all that</hi> Plutarch <hi>in</hi> Greek, <hi>and other in</hi> Latine, <hi>ſince have publiſhed. Mr.</hi> Cleaver <hi>was aſolid Textman. Mr.</hi> Lancaſter <hi>a moſt humble and ſelf denying man; for whereas he was by birth a good Gentleman, and had been Fellow of</hi> Kings <hi>Colledge in</hi> Cambridge, <hi>where being called to ſundry Lectures, and Speeches, he delivered himſelf in as pure</hi> Latine, <hi>to uſe the words of that Maſter of Speech Dr.</hi> Collins, <hi>as ever</hi> Tully <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf uttered, having no Notes before him, but what he wrote on the Nail of his Fiugers: Yet this man thus accompliſhed contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a Living under forty pounds</hi> per annum, and <hi>made no noiſe of any Learning at all.</hi> To theſe I might add, Mr. <hi>Hilderſham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> and others, men
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95459:14"/>famous in their generation, and yet in ſome things, ſome more ſome leſs diſſatisfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="consideration">
               <head>6. Conſid. <hi>That divers diſſenters in former times have notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding found favour with the Biſhops.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Some of thoſe before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med were never deprived of their Benefices, for Non-Conformity, as <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> the Martyrologiſt, and Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi> Others were for a long time by connivance continued in their places and Imployments although but half Conformiſts. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity was not rigorouſly preſſed by Arch-Biſhop <hi>Grindall;</hi> nor were all Nonconformiſts thruſt out of all imployment in the dayes of Arch Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> though himſelf a Champion for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. When Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelf, who had written againſt Conformity, and brandiſhed pens with the Arch-Biſhop in the cauſe, yet was by him quietly ſuffered to injoy an Hoſpital at <hi>Warwick.</hi> Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> ſaid to be the Father of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> did notwithſtanding injoy his Living of a Church in <hi>Northampton</hi> Shire (a Parſonage of good value) to his dying day. And Doctor <hi>Fuller</hi> informs us that Biſhop <hi>Williams</hi> when he was Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> procured a Licenſe from King <hi>James</hi> under the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> for Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> to Preach, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Inconformity as to ſome Ceremonies. And Biſhop <hi>Rudd</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> declares in his Speech to the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that thoſe things, meaning Conformity to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, were not ſo extreamly urged, but that many learned Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers injoyed their liberty herein in the dayes of the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (which was Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi>) condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally that they did not by word or deed openly diſgrace or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the State eſtabliſhed. Concerning Mr. <hi>Hilderſham,</hi> I find in the Hiſtory of his life, that he was frequently ſilenced, and yet frequenly by the favour or connivance of the Biſhops, permitted to Preach publickly: He was ſilenced in <hi>June,</hi> 1590. and reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in <hi>January</hi> 1591. Again he was deprived and ſilenced by Biſhop <hi>Chaderton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, April</hi> 24. 1605. for refuſal of Subſcription and Conformity: yet after ſome time by the conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and favour of Biſhop <hi>Overton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> he Preached ſometimes in that Diocefs, and was the main upholder of two famous Exerciſes, at <hi>Burton</hi> in <hi>Stafford</hi>-Shire, and at <hi>Repton</hi> in <hi>Derby</hi>-Shire, for livers years. In <hi>January</hi> 1608. by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95459:14"/>the favour of Biſhop <hi>Barlow</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> he was allowed to Preach again at <hi>Aſhby,</hi> where he was formerly, and ſo continued from <hi>January</hi> 31, 1608. to <hi>November</hi> the 12th 1611. In <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1611. He was ſilenced by Biſhop <hi>Neales</hi> means, then Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litehſield,</hi> who complained to the King of him, infomuch that the King commanded the Arch-Biſhop to write to the Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi> to ſend for Mr. <hi>Hilderſham,</hi> and to ſilence him, which was done accordingly. <hi>April</hi> the 22. 1613. he was judicially ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed and injoined in and by the High Commiſſion, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Catechiſing of his own family only, he ſhould not any time hereafter, Preach, Catechiſe, or uſe any of the Offices or Function of a Miniſter publickly or privately, until he ſhould be lawfully roſtored and releaſed of his ſaid ſuſpenſion. <hi>June</hi> 20. 1625. he was Licenced by Doctor <hi>Ridley</hi> then Vicar General to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to Preach in the Diocefs of <hi>Lincoln, London,</hi> and <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield,</hi> under the Seal of that Office.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>March</hi> 25. 1630. he was ſilenced again, and ſo continued till <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 2. 1631. when he began to preach again, and continued till <hi>December</hi> 27. 1631. which was the laſt time he preached, ſoon after he ſell ſick and died.</p>
               <p>Concerning Mr. <hi>Dod.</hi> I find in his life, that he was ſuſpended from his Miniſtry at <hi>Hanwill</hi> by Doctor <hi>Bridges</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Oxford;</hi> that after he preached at <hi>Fenny Compton</hi> in <hi>Warwick</hi>-Shire, from thence he removed to <hi>Canons Aſhby</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> where he lived quietly divers years, preached over the whole Prophecy of <hi>Douitl,</hi> afterwards he was ſilenced from Preaching at <hi>Aſhby</hi> upon a complaine made againſt him by Biſhop <hi>Neal</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> who commanded Arch-Biſhop <hi>Abbot</hi> to ſilence him. After the death of King <hi>James,</hi> his liberty was procured for preaching again publickly by Mr. <hi>Knightly,</hi> and then he was ſettled at <hi>Fauſley,</hi> where he preached twice every Lords day. By theſe two laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances it appears, that every ſtroke of the <hi>Croſier</hi> formerly did not cauſe a perfect <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> and prove mortal, though it made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſpeech leſs for a time, yet by the Keys of the Church, their Mouths were often times opened again, and they were able to ſpeak and preach as formerly. And here I could name, if it were fit to do ſo, a great man of our own Church, who was one alſo of great Moderation towards diffenters, and who when he came to dye,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95459:15"/>never, that I heard of, repented the great Latitude or comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiveneſs of his Charity. May the Mantle of that <hi>Elijah</hi> fall on <hi>Eliſha</hi> his Succeſſor, as I hope it will, and on all the Fathers and Brethren of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as I pray it may, that ſo there may be no complaining in our Streets, that ſo peace may be within our Walls, and Proſperity within our Palaces, that there may be glory to God in the Higheſt, and on earth peace to men and good will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="consideration">
               <head>7. Conſid. <hi>That the Parliament in the beginning of the late War declared for the defence and ſafety of his Majeſties perſon, and their abhorreney to be thought to deſign either the depoſition or death of his ſacred Majeſty:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Or elſe it had been impoſſible for them to have gained the people as they did. Preſently after the Battel at <hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,</hi> in a declaration by them publiſhed, they expreſs their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation for the ſafety of his Majeſties Perſon and his Children, and their ſorrow that they had been in any danger there. In which Battel, tis credibly reported, that when Sir <hi>William Balfore</hi> who commanded a Brigade of Horſe in that Battel, was ready to charge part of the Royal Army with his Horſe, perceiving his Majeſty to be amongſt them in that Squadron, and fearing leaſt his Royal Perſon might have been otherwiſe endangered, wheeled off, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out attempting to make any impreſſion there; whereupon by ſome he was complained of, but acquitted from cenſure or blame by the Parliament. And I my ſelf knew ſome ſince, Non-conformiſt Miniſters, who made it their buſineſs to ſtir up ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the old Army to join with ſome of his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and to have endeavoured the reſcue of his Majeſties Perſon after he was ſcized on in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight.</hi> Sure it was the fear the Army had, that the Parliament would agree with his Majeſty, which made them ſo garble the Parliament in <hi>December</hi> 1648. The <hi>London</hi> Presbyterian Miniſters laboured to ſave his Majeſties Crown and Life. And the Miniſters of ſome Lectures in the Country, framed and preſented to the General and his Councel of Officers, their humble advice, with all zeal and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs diſſwading them with Scripture Reaſon, and the Conſcience of Oaths, from depoſing his Majeſty, or embrewing their hands in his blood: It was no Proteſtant Miniſter, or Presbyter, but a Roman Prieſt and Confeſſor, we are told, that when he ſaw the fatal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95459:15"/>ſtroke given, flouriſhed with his Sword, and ſaid, <hi>Now the greateſt Enemy we have in the world is gone.</hi> And how Dr. <hi>Peter Du Moulin,</hi> and upon what grounds, laid the Murther of his late Majeſty on the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the Reader may ſee in his Anſwer to <hi>Philanax An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicus,</hi> pag. 58, 59. &amp;c. And if the Teſtimony of the <hi>French</hi> may be accepted and why not, for Standers by often ſee more than Gameſters, we have the Letters of Monſieur <hi>Daille,</hi> of Monſieur <hi>Gache,</hi> and of the <hi>Marchioneſs</hi> of <hi>Turin,</hi> to clear the Presbyterians from this horrid Act. And ſome there are at home, who are ſo noble, though themſelves fought under the Royal Standard, as yet acknowledge that the Presbyterians hated this Murther as much as themſelves,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="consideration">
               <head>8. Conſid. <hi>That the Nou-conforming Presbyterians had both their hearts and hands in the Reſtauration of His Majeſty to His Royal Throne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians did concur with and aſſiſt the <hi>Scots;</hi> ſome in perſon, others with their Purſes, moſt with their Prayers, in bringing His Majeſty to His ancient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the year 1650. for which endeavours, Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbous</hi> loſt their Heads by the Axe, and for which Zeal for His Majeſty, many more were impriſoned and condemned, though not executed. Mr. <hi>Cawton</hi> was Indicted of High Treaſon for Praying for His Majeſty that now is, as King of <hi>England</hi> in thoſe dayes. Mr. <hi>George Firmin</hi> in Print tells us, that he and ſome others in thoſe times Prayed even in their Congregations for the afflicted Royal Family: Mr. <hi>Kirby</hi> a <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> Miniſter was brought up to <hi>London</hi> and impriſoned for Praying publickly for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by Name. Yea, ſo great and publick was the <hi>London</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Zeal and Loyalty, that there was a Pamphlet Printed, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A Mourning Lecture for our Morning Lecturers,</hi> calling them the cloudy Clergy, and Beadſmen for the King of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Moſt certain it is alſo, that our <hi>French</hi> Neighbours the Proteſtants there, looked on the Presbyterians of <hi>England,</hi> a little before His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Reſtauration, as poſſeſſed of the power, and ſitting at the Hem in <hi>England. That illuſtrious Aſſembly,</hi> i. e. the Parliament ſaith Monſieur <hi>Drelincourt,</hi> in his Letter from <hi>Paris, April</hi> 3. 1660. afterward Printed; <hi>who would have preſerved to the King his life, and his Royalty, was without doubt very far from deſigning to rob his Children of that right which is conveyed to them by a continued Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95459:16"/>in their Royal Family for many Ages.</hi> And again in the ſame Letter he thus expreſſes himſelf. <hi>God intruſts at this day you Presbyterians, the Gentlemen now in Power, with the honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of our Church; for if without the intervening of any Forreign Power they recall this Prince and ſeat Him in His Throne, they acquire to themſelves and their poſterity immortal Glory, and ſtop their Mouths for ever, who charge us falſely as enemies of Royalty, make appear that the Maxime of No Biſhop, No King, is injuriouſly imputed to us.</hi> Now what was deſired by this Letter, was done within a ſhort time, and by the Power, Intereſts, and Endeavours of thoſe here called Presbyterians. The Royaliſts at that time, not for want of Zeal or Loyalty, but through Policy and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence not appearing ſo publickly, leaſt thereby upon that account or occaſſion, the deſigh ſhould miſcarry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="consideration">
               <head>9. Conſid. <hi>Many Biſhops, Clergymen and Scholars, though Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts to the late times; yet injoyed Places or Profit notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Biſhops by Ordinance of Parliament were to have for their Lives 200 <hi>
                     <abbr>l</abbr> per ann.</hi> each of them. Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> that Learned Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> received a Thouſand pound, which was given him by the Parliament, and with which he purchaſed (if I miſtake not) an Annuity of 200 <hi>
                     <abbr>l</abbr> per ann.</hi> for his life. The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Brownrig,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Skinner,</hi> had places of Imployment and Profit in thoſe times. Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> kept <hi>Boothby Pagnel</hi> Parſonage during the Troubles. Many in ſeveral Colledges in <hi>Cambridge</hi> kept their Places without ever taking the Covenant. Dr. <hi>Collins</hi> was ſuffer'd to keep his Place of <hi>Regius</hi> Profeſſor without ever taking the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. So did all the Fellows of <hi>Emmanuel</hi> Colledge, except Dr. <hi>Soreby</hi> (who was Ejected on another accompt) continue in their Fellowſhips without taking the Covenant. Some Fellows were put into <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge by Ordinance of Parliament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having the Covenant impoſed on them, as I have heard. Further in the Viſitation of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford;</hi> the Maſters and Fellows there were not Ejected for the Refuſal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but upon another ſcore, namely Non-ſubmiſſion to the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Let me add to the Premiſes on this Conſideration, that the two Houſes by Ordinance of Parliament granted a fifth part for the maintenance of Miniſters Wives and Children. Yea, that the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95459:16"/>Junto, after the Parliament was Garbled, made an Act as they call'd it, <hi>April 5th.</hi> 1660. inabling, and requiring their Trullees for Biſhops, Deans and Chapters Lands, to diſpoſe thereof for and towards the relief, maintenance and ſupport of ſuch Biſhops, Deans, Prebendaries, Singing men, Choriſters, and other Members, Officers, and perſons deſtitute of Maintenance, diſtributing and apportioning the ſame adcording to the wants and neceſſities of ſuch perſons to whom the ſaid diſpoſition ſhall be made as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and according to further ditections as they ſhall receive from the Parllament or Authority derived from it. And further may it be conſidered, that in King <hi>Joſiah</hi> his Reformation, although the Prieſts of the High places were put from the Service, yet they were ſtill permitted to eat of the portion belonging to the Prieſts, <hi>viz</hi> of the Unleavened bread amongſt their Brethren, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23 9. they had ſome proviſion for their maintenance. As alſo what we read in our own Story <hi>viz.</hi> That in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. liberal Penſions were allowed by the King to Abbots, Priors, and Monks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the diſſolution of Abbies and Monaſteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="consideration">
               <head>10. Conſid. <hi>It is declared to be the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>in the</hi> 34 <hi>Article of our Religion. That every particular or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church hath Authority to ordain, change and aboliſh Ceremonies, or Rites of the Church; ordained only by mans Authority, ſo that all things be done to Edification.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'Tis the obſervation of a Learned Gentleman deceafect, late a Member of the Preſent Parliament, in an Epiſtle Dedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ry to His Majeſty, That the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> alb it they hold themſelves infallible in their Chair, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels inerrable. Yet they all accord that their publick Miſſals and Liturgies, though made and confirmed by their Joine advice, with greateſt care and diligence, are amendable, alterable, upon juſt occaſions— He inſtanceth in ſeveral amendments and alterations by Pope <hi>Pins</hi> the 5th. And he obſerves that the ſame Pope, did think fit to reform ſeveral things in the new Miſſal as to the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to alter and diſpenſe with it in no leſs than 21 par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, notwithſtanding his former Bulls and Prohibitions, And after that, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th. his Imthediate Succeſſor, granted ſeveral other Diſpenſations and Amendments of this Miſſal in ſundry particulars compriſed in his Bull.—And that which ought to be of more Authority with us in <hi>England,</hi> is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95459:17"/>(what I ſhall ſubjoyn to our Doctrine declared in a branch of the 34th. Article of Religion formerly cited <hi>(the agreement of our Biſhops and Doctors convened at the Dean of</hi> Weſtminſters <hi>Lodgings in the beginning of the Parliament</hi> 1640. <hi>the Perſons were the Biſhops of</hi> Lincoln, Armagh, Durham, Exeter, <hi>Doctor</hi> Samuel Ward, <hi>Dr.</hi> Prideaux, <hi>Dr.</hi> Twiſſe, <hi>Dr.</hi> Siunderſon, <hi>Dr.</hi> Featly, <hi>Dr.</hi> Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig, <hi>Dr.</hi> Holdſworth, <hi>Dr.</hi> Hacket, <hi>and others. The advice they gave, amongſt many other things, was, that the Veſtments required by the firſt Liturgy of King</hi> Edward <hi>the 6th ſhould not be required, and the Rubrick in that caſe to be altered. That the Croſs in Baptiſm be either explained or quite diſuſed. That a Rubrick be inſerted to declare that kneeling at the Communion is required only in Relation to the Prayer of diſtribution, Preſerve thy Body and Soul unto everlaſtling life.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> his <hi>Cyp. Angl.</hi> p. 444, 445. And now my hearty deſire is, that the Prudence, Moderation, and Condeſcenſion of theſe great Scholars and good Men for the Peace of the Church, might turn the hearts of all in Place and Power, to incline them to Moderation and Indulgence at ſuch a time as this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="consideration">
               <head>11. Conſid. <hi>That if the new Impoſitions were removed, and that partition wall of Ceremonies pull'd down, and this veil rent away by Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Authority from the face of the Church, or reſerved only for the caſe of the Mother Churches, I mean the Cathedrals. Many Thouſands who now ſeparate from our publick Aſſemblies, would with one heart and voice joyn with us.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We Proteſtants juſtly blame the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for that having the Keys of Purgatory at his Girdle, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſuffers ſo many Thouſand Souls to lye in Flames ſome Hundreds of years, where he can ſo eaſily grant a Goal-delivery, and ſet them at liberty. And if Sin, and particularly the Sin of Schiſm, be worſe than Hell it ſelf, as indeed all Sin is, then I would humbly recommend to the Father of our Countrey, to the Fathers of our Church, &amp; to our worthy Patriots in the Parliament, the <hi>removal of thoſe By-matters;</hi> that ſo they may thereby prevent ſo many Thouſands from incurring either the fault, the blot, or the puniſhment of Schiſmaticks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="consideration">
               <head>12. Conſid. <hi>That the uſe of force or violent courſes for By-matters in Religion ought by all lawful wayes and means to be ſhunned and avoided.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:95459:17"/>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Heywood</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Doleman</hi> the perſonated Papiſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. concerning violent courſes in matters of Religion, writes thus, hereupon ſuch cruel Calamities have enſued in moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> with ſo little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to that cauſe for whoſe ſupportance force was offered, that all the chief Writers of our Age, are now reduced to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer opinion, affirming with <hi>Arnobius, that Religion is of Power ſufficient for it ſelf, with</hi> Tertullian <hi>alſo,</hi> Lactantius, Caſſiodorus, Joſephus, <hi>St.</hi> Bernard, <hi>and others; that it muſt be perſwaded, and not inforced.</hi> See Mr. <hi>Joh. Good.</hi> Anſw. to the <hi>Antapol.</hi> p. 233, and 234. Conformable to which Doctrine was the Practice of Biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> See his Replication to the Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> p. 152, 153. where he ſaith, <hi>That the Earl of</hi> Strafford <hi>Lord Lieutenant of</hi> Ireland <hi>did commit much to my hands, the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Regiment of that Church for the ſpace of eight years. In all that time; let him name but one</hi> Roman <hi>Catholick, that ſuffer'd either Death or Impriſonment, or ſo much as a Pecuniary Mulct of Twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for his Religion, upon any penal Statute, if he cannot, as I am ſure he cannot,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I read that when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> drove the <hi>Indians</hi> to Baptiſm, as we do Sheep to waſhing, when the white Linnen they gave them to be Baptized in, was foul, the Baptized <hi>Indians</hi> would ſtreight renounce their Chriſtianity, except they might have new white Garments given them. This inſtance may mind us, that Methods of force and compulſion are not the way to make good Chriſtians, but Time-ſervers and Hypocrites, rather than real Converts.</p>
               <p>The Premiſes conſider'd, and that by our Breaches, way be not made for Popery to enter. 'Tis heartily deſired of Diſſenters, that they would be earneſt in their Prayers to God, and their Petitions to men that there may a healing of our breaches. And to this end, that none of them do any thing, or leave any thing undone, through humour, croſſeneſs, or peeviſhneſs; that none of them this matter or in reference to the Church, be like the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> in reference to the Kingdom of Heaven, of whom 'tis ſaid, that they would not enter in themſelves, and hindred thoſe that were ready to enter, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.52.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95459:18"/>
               <p>Of the Fathers of the Church, 'tis humbly beg'd, that they would in relation to Diſſenters imitate the Father of the Prodigal, who when his Son was yet afar off, ran to meet him, fell on his neck, and kiſſed him.</p>
               <p>Of His moſt excellent Majeſty and the Two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'tis moſt humbly Prayed, that they would pleaſe to remember, That there is as much Power exerciſed or exerted in abrogating a Law at the Humble deſires of Subjects, as in making a Law at their Requeſts.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95459:18"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT to Conformiſt and Non-Conformiſt Miniſters.</head>
            <p>LEt all things be done with Charity: <hi>And often think of the Anſwer of pious Mr.</hi> Greenham <hi>to Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> Cecil, <hi>when he asked him on which ſide the blame lay in the great Rent 'twixt the Biſhops and Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts.</hi> The Fault, <hi>ſaid Mr.</hi> Greenham, is on both ſides, and on neither ſide; for, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> the Godly wiſe on both ſides, bear with each other, and concenter in the Main; but then there be ſelſiſh, peeviſh Spirits on both ſides ſome, and theſe make the quarrel.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
